Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is ל"ג, Lamed Gimmel,
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah 33. We pick up on דף ל"ג עמוד
א', daf Lamed Gimmel amud aleph, about twelve lines down at the
two
dots. והבאים מותרין. Vhaba'im mutarin. And we're explaining his משנה, mishna, very
long משנה mishna that dealt with different types of scenarios and circumstances
or whatever where various foods or moneys or so on that were
associated with עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah are forbidden. So right now we're
in this section that actually said that those that are that when
you're going and you're doing business that when people are going on
a type of a pilgrimage, an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah pilgrimage, that
you cannot do business with them on their
way going, because then it's sort of like the very beginning of
the מסכת, masechet, it's like three days before their holidays, even if
this isn't three days before the holidays, they're going to have that
joy from that interaction, that business transaction or whatever and bring it
into their worship that they're heading towards. But the משנה mishna continues
and we dealt with that yesterday. But the משנה mishna continues והבאים
מותרין, vhaba'im mutarin, when they are returning from their pilgrimage, then they're
just going home. So then you can do business with them. So
אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, לא שנו אלא
שאין קשורים זה בזה.
lo shanu
ela she'ein kshurin zeh bazeh. אבל קשורים זה בזה אסורין. Aval kshurin
zeh bazeh asurin. That's only when they're coming back and they're coming
back separate from one another. But if they're all coming back bonded
together, doesn't literally mean connected with a rope, but they're coming back
in groups, like people take these tour groups to Jerusalem, these Christian
tour groups and so on, so you see them all coming back
in a group. So אימא דעתו לחזור. eima daito lachzor. So that
means that they're doing it as a whole social thing or they're
deeply committed. It wasn't just a personal thing and a one-time thing.
So therefore you have to be afraid that they're going to go
back and do it again. Now it's still not clear to me
because even if they're going to go back and do it again,
it doesn't mean they're going to do it again now, they might
do it again next year. So who cares if you're doing business
with them now? But
maybe he just feels that they're still in the process of some
degree, not exactly clear. All right, now we move on to a
completely different issue which gets us really to important discussions about
about סתם יינם stam yeinam and wine and whether it and also
the basically absorption of different vessels and particularly in the case of
wine this is about the issue about whether vessels can absorb even
when they're cold because the normal principle is that you need heat
for the transfer of taste. But particularly also when the גמרא Gemara
was dealing with pottery vessels and stuff is in the vessel for
a long time and that's porous, that basically leads to concerns that
the vessel absorbed the taste of the wine. So the משנה mishna
speaks about that if you have
these נודות, nodot, these flasks, these like leather flasks that was used,
and the קנקניהם, kankanehem, which is the pottery vessels, then and they
used them and they absorbed wine and then you put your wine
into it, so רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir said so the wine, the
non-kosher wine came back out and now your wine is forbidden in
הנאה, hana'ah, even in deriving benefit, and the חכמים Chachamim said no,
it's just forbidden to actually drink it but not in הנאה, hana'ah,
so that's an interesting question right there about the status of when
there's תערובת ta'arovet of יין נסך yayin nesech or even this יין
נסך yayin nesech that's derived that the taste was absorbed and came
back out, that the חכמים Chachamim are lenient to say that it's
only forbidden in drinking and not in הנאה. hana'ah. But the גמרא
Gemara doesn't actually focus on that debate. The גמרא Gemara zooms in
to focus on the question about what type of vessels absorb. So
let's take a look. And again, emphasizing that this is cold. תנו
רבנן, Tannu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught. נודות עובדי כוכבים, Nodot ovdei kochavim,
so if you're dealing with these leather wine flasks, גרודים חדשים מותרין.
grudim chadashim mutarin. If they
are like peeled, meaning that they've never been, the inside has not
been lined with pitch, which as we'll see is something that they
did, so it's just the straight leather and it's new, they've only
been used recently by the non-Jew, then it's permissible, they don't absorb
the taste, it's all cold. However, ישנים, yeshanim, if they are old,
meaning that they've been used for a while by the non-Jew, it
doesn't exactly describe here how old is old,
ומזופפים, umezufafim, which רש"י Rashi reads 'or they are tarred', they are
lined with tar, which is very porous, so more than the leather,
אסורין, asurin, then it is forbidden, then those are considered to have
absorbed the wine. עובדי כוכבים ריבבן ועבדן. Ovdei kochavim rivavan ve'ivdan. Now
let's say the non-Jew is the one that sort of put in
the pitch and the tar of the inside of this leather flask,
ונתן לתוכו יין, venasan ltocho yayin, and he also poured wine in
because apparently what they would do is that they would put in
the wine to negate the bad taste of the pitch, presumably the
pitch was in order that it should last, be
more... pan, then often you'll find they have been pre-seasoned and you
have to make sure that they're not pre-seasoned with like טרף treif
oils. Okay so here too it's been pre-seasoned with wine. ונתן לתוכן
יין venasan letochan yayin וישראל עומד על גביו veYisrael omed al gabav
but if a Jew is observing, אינו חושש. ein choishesh. You don't
have to worry about it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says what
do you mean you don't have to worry about it? כי מאחר
דעובד כוכבים נתן לתוכה יין ki meachar deoved kochavim nosan letocha yayin
if the non-Jew is putting wine in it, כי ישראל עומד על
גביו מאי הוה ki Yisrael omed al gabav mai hava who cares
that a Jew is observing it? He's still pouring wine and shouldn't
we be concerned that that's like יין נסך, yein nesech, you know,
he's pouring it. Now it's not exactly clear whose wine it is,
you know, if it could also be his wine. So who cares
if a Jew is watching? Once it's his wine, it's forbidden. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב פפא הכי קאמר. amar Rav Papa
hachi ka amar. Here's what it means. עובד כוכבים ריבן ועיבדן oved
kochavim rivan veivdan וישראל נותן לתוכן יין veYisrael nosen letochan yayin no,
he changes it. He says the non-Jew is putting in the pitch
and the Jew is pouring in wine. וישראל אחר עומד על גביו
veYisrael acher omed al gabav and another Jew is observing, ואינו חושש
ve'ein choisesh that's okay and you don't have to worry about it.
So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, מאחר דישראל נותן לתוכן
יין meachar deYisrael noten letochan yayin if it's the Jew that's putting
the wine, וישראל אחר עומד על גביו למה לי Yisrael acher omed
al gabav lama li who needs some other Jew to be observing?
It's all kosher wine. גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא אגב טרדיה מנסך
ולאו אדעתיה. dilma agav tirdei minaseich velav adaitei. Maybe because the Jew
who's pouring in the wine, no he's doing he's very focused on
his professional work of pouring it in exactly at the right time
in the right way when they're pouring on in the in the
pitch. So he's not paying attention to what the non-Jew is doing,
and the non-Jew might use that as opportunity to like stick his
hand into the wine and turn it into a moment of sprinkling
wine for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So therefore you need another Jew
to observe to make sure that does not happen. Okay, that's a
good answer but that is a re-reading of the ברייתא. braisa. So
now let's see where the גמרא Gemara says. רב
זביד אמר, Rav Zvid amar, רב זביד Rav Zvid says לעולם כדקאמרת
מעיקרא. le'olam kede'amras meikara. No, it's really like the ברייתא braisa was
originally taught that the non-Jew can pour wine into it. והכא vehacha
and here's why it's okay. בעידנא דקשדי ליה be'idna dekeshadi lei when
he is pouring in the wine, נעשה כזורק מים לטיט. naasei kezoreik
mayim letit. It's like you're pouring wine into like plaster, it's like
you're pouring it, you know, to be הולך לאיבוד holeich le'ibud to
go to waste, you're pouring it into pitch and into tar. Now
why does that make it okay? So רש"י Rashi says, well what
it really means, this doesn't fit so perfectly the words of the
גמרא, Gemara, but what it really means is is that since it's
being mixed with the pitch then basically the pitch sort of, you
know, not only absorbs the wine but somewhat counteracts it and causes
it all to be destroyed or dried up so that there's no
more any taste of wine to go back into the, you know,
to the to the wine that you're storing in the flask. That's
not exactly the language of like focusing on the act of pouring.
It's actually focusing on the fact that when mixed with the pitch
it basically gets destroyed.
Others, you know, read it based on like the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that
it actually means that no, clearly this is not an act of
ניסוך nisuch because it's an act of destroying, he's pouring it into
pitch. Of course that's not exactly clear how that would help if
it was his wine. His wine once it's his wine it's אסור,
assur, but that could help if it was if it was our
wine that he was pouring. Okay, so that's this point. It's like
he's pouring it to be destroyed.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay.
אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, שמע
מינה מדרב זביד shema mina midrav Zvid we can infer from רב
זביד, Rav Zvid, האי עובד כוכבים דשדי חמרא לבי מלחי hai oved
kochavim deshadi chamra lebei milchei if a non-Jew is putting wine into
the salt, and I'm going back to explain those words לבי מלחי
bei milchei but רש"י Rashi says it just literally means salt, דישראל
deYisrael of a Jew, שרי shari it's permissible, because maybe the salt
also burns it and destroys its taste. So גמרא Gemara says what
do you mean? מתקיף לה רב אשי, maskif la Rav Ashi, מי
דמי? mi dami? How can you compare it? התם קאזיל לאיבוד hasam
ka'azil le'ibud in the first case it's actively being destroyed, הכא לא
קאזיל לאיבוד hacha lo ka'azil le'ibud here it's not being destroyed, the
taste remains in the salt. So for רש"י Rashi the focus here
it's just about salt and then and, you know, and
and the basic answer is well you can still taste it, it
doesn't destroy the taste. But תוספות Tosafot says that we never would
have made that comparison. Of course it's completely different pouring something into
pitch and pouring it into salt. So תוספות Tosafot says we're not
talking about pouring it into salt. We're talking about you're going to
the place where the salt is being made and where, you know,
there's the fires that are burning in order to, I don't know,
I don't exactly know how salt is made, but to dissolve it,
you know, and and allow you to to sort of process it
and you're pouring the water in when the fires are burning so
it's actually the claim is that the fires are destroying it and
it's not getting absorbed. And then the answer is no, it still
can get absorbed in that scenario more than it can in the
case of the pitch. Okay. It's actually interesting, the last line of
תוספות Tosafot he says like this, he says or two lines from
the bottom in תוספות Tosafot he says ואומר רבנו תם, veomer Rabbeinu
Tam, כי האי אתקפתא דרב אשי אינו אלא דחויי בעלמא. ki hai
atkifta deRav Ashi ein elu dechuyei be'alma. This challenge—oh, your case of
the salt isn't exactly like our case of the pitch or of
the salt mines, the salt
processing—כלומר, k'lomar, he says that's only saying you can't prove it. כלומר
מדברי רב זביד לא תשמע, k'lomar midivrei Rav Zvid lo tishma, you
can't prove it from Rav Zvid's teaching. אבל מכל מקום הלכה כרב
פפא, aval mikol makom halacha k'Rav Papa, but really he's right, if
you're pouring it in a context in which, you know, there's this,
you know, this fire going and it's being sort of poured on
near the fire, so the fire destroys it. ומתוך כך umitoch kach
and here's an interesting practical application, התירו המלח
אף על פי שרגילים שמשים עליו דם בשעת רתיחה ללבנו. hitiro hamelach
af al pi sheragilim shemasim alav dam b'sha'at reticha l'lavno. So Rabbeinu
Tam, they say we permit to use salt that's being processed, you
know, by the non-Jews, even though sometimes what they do is that
when it's bubbling and boiling, they put in a little blood in
order to whiten it. Now, you could say, you know, it's a
tiny little blood, it's not נותן טעם, noten ta'am, but here he
gives the reason that everything is so hot, you know, in the
processing
that actually, maybe it's so close to the fire that it actually
gets destroyed. And actually it's interesting that even today in certain cases
of food industries they'll put in a little blood to do have
certain effects. Okay. Now the Gemara says like this:
where are we? Okay.
בר
אדיתיא, Bar Addi Taya, so this, you know, this
who was an Arab, this Bar Addi the Arab, בר אדיתיא Bar
Addi Taya אנס הנהו זיקי מדרב יצחק בר יוסף. anas hanhu ziki
mi-Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef. He forcibly seized, you know, these leather wine
skins, wine flasks,
wine flasks from Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef. רמא בהו חמרא, rama behu
chamra, he then used it to keep his wine, ואהדרינהו ניהליה, v'ahadrinhu
nihaleh, and then when he was done using it, he returned it.
Okay, so here you basically have a question, wine that was put
into a wine flask and used for a certain period of time,
does the wine flask absorb? So אזל שאל בי מדרשא, azal she'al
bei midrasha, he went and he asked in the Beis Medrash. אמר
ליה רבי ירמיה, amar leh Rabbi Yirmeya, Rabbi Yirmeya said, כך הורה
רב אמי, kach hora Rav Ami, this is what Rav Ami taught:
הלכה למעשה, halacha l'ma'aseh, for practical matter, ממלאים מים שלושה ימים ומערן.
memal'im mayim shlosha yamim u-m'aran.
The way you kasher it is you fill it with water three
days and then you spill out the water. אבל אמר רבא, aval
amar Rava, צריכה לערן מעת לעת, tzricha l'aran me'et l'et, and you
have to do it every 24 hours. So it's three days, but
24 hours, then you spill it out, then it maybe absorbs back
some of the wine taste, but then you've got to get rid
of that and throw it out and get fresh water to absorb
some more and do it a third time. So there's two assumptions
here. Number one is that it absorbed, which isn't so clear why
because it's not brand new, you know, the Gemara before said that
it was—that when it's brand new and only
used briefly, it doesn't absorb. Here it's been used, but it's been
used by a Jew. So one could have raised the question that,
and we will get to this later in the Gemara, that since
it was already heavily used by a Jew, maybe that should mean
that there's no more left for it to absorb. But the Gemara
here is not assuming that, is assuming that it did absorb even
if it had previously been used by a Jew, and is also
now saying there's a way to kasher. And maybe this is a
way to always kasher problematic flasks and so on, we'll see about
that. And that's through this filling water, you know, over 72 hours.
Now some people might be familiar with this, some people practice this
with their glasses for Pesach, you know,
and this is not a general way of kashering, but it's a
way of kashering when we're concerned that things absorbed even with cold,
which is particularly a concern here we have about סתם יינם. stam
yeinam. Whether
it's a concern that we should have with glass for, you know,
for drinks is a different question. But anyway, but that's where we
get it from, a way of kashering things that absorbed with cold.
Okay. ואמר רבא, va-amar Rava, and Rava said, צריכה לערן מעת לעת.
tzricha l'aran me'et l'et. So I just said that, you have to
do it pour it out every 24 hours. סברו מינה הני מילי
דידן. savru minah hani mili didan. We thought that that that we're
lenient, that what we allow this kashering of water for 72 hours,
you know, three periods of 24, that's when it's our flasks that
have already been used with wine, so the amount they absorbed when
the non-Jew took it and used it is a minimal amount.
אבל דידהו, aval didehu, if it's a flask that ממש mamash has
been used by a non-Jew and it's only been used for non-kosher
wine over the course of I don't know 10 years, so there
you would say לא, lo, there that type of kashering would not
work, because the Mishnah just says it's forbidden, it never tells you
how you can kasher it. So כי אתא רבין אמר רבי שמעון
בן לקיש, ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, but when
Ravin came he said in the name of Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish:
אחד שלנו ואחד שלהם. echad shelanu v'echad shelahem. No, whether it's ours
or theirs, we assume that this thing with the water is a
way to kasher things that absorb through cold. Now, סבר רב אחא
בריה דרבא קמיה דרב אשי למימר, savar Rav Acha brei d'Rava kamei
d'Rav Ashi l'meimar, so Rav Acha son of Rava thought in discussing
this in front of Rav Ashi, he thought to say. הני מילי
נודות. hani milei nodot. Okay fine, but maybe this new way of
כשר kashering works with leather flasks, maybe even if they have pitch
in them, but אבל קנקנין aval kankanin when you come to pottery
vessels, those are jugs, that's very porous. No, that wouldn't כשר kasher
it. So אמר ליה רב אשי לא שנא נודות ולא שנא קנקנים,
amar lei Rav Ashi lo shena nodot velo shena kankanin, it doesn't
matter. The same way it absorbed through cold, it can also the
taste can also come back out through cold. Now of course there's
a little bit of a difference. I mean it absorbed through cold
over many many years of use, right? So it's all going to
come out in in the course of seventy-two hours? Not so clear,
but that's what we are arguing. Okay. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our
Rabbis taught, קנקנים של עובדי כוכבים חדשים גרודים. kankanin shel ovdei kochavim
chadashim grudim. Now we're moving, this is going to be very parallel
to the earlier discussion about leather flasks, but this is now going
to be about like pottery jugs. Okay so pottery jugs or jars
of of non-Jews, חדשים גרודים, chadashim grudim, if they're new and they're
untarred, you know, unlined, מותרים, mutarim, then it's okay because it's only
been used very briefly and it hasn't really absorbed. ישנים ומזופפים, yeshanim
umezufafim, if
they are if they are old and and or tarred, the way
רש״י Rashi reads it, אסורים, asurim, then they are forbidden because again
if it's old then it's had plenty of time to absorb and
if it's tarred then the tar is porous and absorbs. עובד כוכבים
נותן לתוכן יין. oved kochavim noten letochan yayin. Now if a non-Jew
has put wine in it, ישראל נותן לתוכן מים. Yisrael noten letochan
mayim. A Jew can put water in it. Now this is interesting
because רש״י Rashi reads this as meaning that this is the כשר
kashering that we spoke about a minute ago, which is you know
three days, seventy-two hours, etc. Of course נותן לתוכן מים noten letochan
mayim doesn't necessarily indicate that whole process. Also this is saying explicitly
that that's a type of a כשר kashering that works
for earthenware jars and before we were uncertain about it. But that
at least is the way that רש״י Rashi is explaining this ברייתא
braita to say exactly what we said before, that this water is
a way of כשר kashering it. נותן לתוכן מים. noten letochan mayim.
עובד כוכבים נותן לתוכן יין ישראל נותן לתוכן ציר ומוריס oved kochavim
noten letochan yayin Yisrael noten letochan tzir umoris ואינו חושש. ve'eino choshesh.
And now we have another הלכה halacha that also even after a
non-Jew has used it for wine, a Jew can use it for
like like a fish brine and you know some of these other
types of sharp pungent liquids, and you don't have to be concerned
about the taste of the wine because again רש״י Rashi says that
this pungent strong taste will negate the taste of the wine. You
could also say maybe it's נותן טעם לפגם, noten ta'am lifgam, here's
another type of a concern. But okay רש״י Rashi says it's this
idea of counteracting that taste. Now he says that this is different
than the water because the water is three days, but this is
saying no, immediately you can use these other liquids because they will
negate the taste. So איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, so the גמרא Gemara
says the question was raised
לכתחילה דיעבד. lechatchila di'avad. Is that only לכתחילה lechatchila can you put
these other things in, you know it's sort of like okay you
used it, it was more than twenty-four hours,
נותן טעם לפגם, noten ta'am lifgam, so don't do it לכתחילה lechatchila
but בדיעבד bedi'avad if you already used it we can be okay
with it? Or are we going to allow it even לכתחילה? lechatchila?
So תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, דתני רב זביד detani
Rav Zevid at the top of ל״ג עמוד ב׳ lamed-gimel amud bet
בר אושעיא הלוקח קנקנים מן עובדי כוכבים חדשים נותן לתוכן יין. bar
Oshaya halokei'ach kankanin min ovdei kochavim chadashim noten letochan yayin. So same
thing, you know if these if they are if they are new
newish or whatever of these earthenware jugs, of these pottery jugs, then
they haven't then they haven't really absorbed, so you can go ahead
and use it for wine. ישנים, yeshanim, and if they're old נותן
לתוכן ציר ומוריס לכתחילה. noten letochan tzir umoris lechatchila. You can from
the outset use it with these types of brines, they will negate
the taste of the wine, it's not just a בדיעבד. bedi'avad. Okay
so that's not a כשר, kashering, that's more of a counteracting.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. בעי מיניה רב
יהודה נשיאה מרבי אמי. ba'ei minei Rav Yehuda Nesi'ah meRabbi Ami. So
רב יהודה נשיאה, Rav Yehuda Nesi'ah, grandson of רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi
Yehuda HaNasi, asked from רבי אמי, Rabbi Ami, החזירן לכבשן האש ונתלבנו
מהו? hechziran lechivshan ha'esh venitlabnu mahu? Let's say you've got these you
know pottery vessels and and they absorbed wine and you now put
them back into the urn, not the urn, the what's it called
the kiln, and and you would that be like be considered to
like burn out the taste that is absorbed? Okay and they became
white hot. אמר ליה, amar lei, ציר שורף או לא כל שכן?
tzir soref o lo kol sheken? If we permitted even using just
like this type of brine that that sort of like counteracts the
taste of the wine, then certainly, you know, real fire would be
considered to destroy it. Okay now by the way that also sounds
like, and רש״י Rashi says this explicitly before, that when you use
this brine it's not just that the brine is permitted, the brine
goes in and destroys the taste of the wine and now you
can use it for anything. And that would make it parallel to
the כשר kashering of the water. Okay so he says certainly that
would work, if it works with brine it would work with fire.
איתמר
נמי, itmar nami, was also said, אמר רבי יוחנן ואמרי לה אמר
רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan ve'amrei lah amar Rabbi
Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan, האש, ha'esh, if by the fire, if you
put these vessels into the
fire. Once their inner tar sort of like you know sloughs off,
melts, מהן מותרין, mehen mutarin, they're permissible. Which anyway makes sense because
the whole thing is only absorbed into the tar or maybe primarily
absorbed into the tar. But now the Gemara takes it one step
further. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, לא תימא עד דנתרן, lo
teima ad denasran, don't say that literally they had to totally melt.
אלא אפילו רפוי מרפו, ella afilu rifuy mirpu, even if the tar
only softens, אף אגב דלא נתר, af agav dlo natar, even if
it didn't. Okay, so it's not really about destroying the tar, but
once it had that impact on it, so then we can say
that it destroys the absorbed wine. So okay, one way to kasher
something that absorbs with liquid is with other cold liquids under done
in the right ways, and one way is the classic way of
kashering, you know, using heat. Okay, so now the Gemara says like
this: Now, קינסא, kinsa, what about if you put little like wood
you know like twigs inside of the vessel? You didn't put it
in a kiln, you put it on the inside of the vessel
and you made the fire on the inside. פליגי בה רב אחא
ורבינא, Pligi bah Rav Acha u'Ravina, it's a debate of Rav Acha
and Ravina. חד אסר וחד שרי, Chad asar vechad sharei, one says
it's forbidden, one says it's permissible. והלכתא כמאן דאסר, Ve-hilchata keman de-asar,
and the reason and we rule like the one who forbids it.
Now you might say how's it different than the case of the
fire? So the Gemara is going to get to that.
איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu.
So excuse me, it's not the Gemara doesn't get to it, Rashi
talks about it. And this is an interesting Rashi. Let's look at
the Rashi, three lines from the top: והלכתא כמאן דאסר. ve-hilchata keman
de-asar. So Rashi says: ולא דמי להחזירן בכבשן, velo dami lehachziran bekivshan,
it's not like putting them back into the kiln. דהתם כיון שהסיקן
מבחוץ, dehasam keivan she-hisikan mibachutz, עד שנשרו זפתן, ad shenashru zaftan, there
since the heat was on the outside and then the tar on
it got so hot that the tar on the inside melted, תניית
לבנה אחריס, tanyas levana achris, then the pottery itself got white hot.
אבל הכא כיון שהכניס האור מיד זפתו
נושר. aval hacha keivan shehechnis ha'or miyad zafto nosher. Here you're getting
the tar to like to melt, you know, to soften, but you're
not heating up the pottery. The softening of the tar was only
a measure of how hard you heated up the pottery when the
fire was from the outside. So that's a very nice explanation and
let's just look at Rashi who ties it in practically: ומהכא שמעינן
דהני חביות או קנקנים, umehacha shameinan dehanei chavyos o kankanin, לפי שמכניסם
לקיום. lefi shemachnisam lekiyum. So that if you have certain like you
know barrels or jugs of wine and because they are used to
store wine for a long period of time, so those are a
good case of ישנים, yeshanim, right, they're old and they really absorbed
the wine. So you have to kasher them. לא סגי בהכשר בפנים.
lo sagi behachsher bifnim. You can't, so clearly this was a practical
case, right? They were in the wine, you know, wine business was
major business in the Middle Ages. It's and you know, using old
barrels that you get from the non-Jew. So it's not enough to
fire it up on the inside, בין לשרפם בין לתת בהם מים
חמים, bein lesorfam bein lates bahem mayim chamim, and you can't neither
the other normal way of kashering pouring in hot water. מדאסר בקינסא,
mide'asar bekinsa, דהיינו באור עצמו, dainu be'or atzmo, since it forbids even
using like little pieces of wood,
even fire directly, כל שכן במים חמים, kol shekein bemayim chamim, certainly
you just can't use hot water. Now I should pause and say
this only absorbed cold, so why does normal means of kashering, heat,
hot water work? And the answer is because you normally can't kasher
pottery. Pottery is considered to absorb and never give out. So on
the one hand it's only cold, but on the other hand it's
pottery. So therefore those forms do not work. So what can you
do? אבל אם אפשר לשרפן מבחוץ שרי, aval im efshar lesorfam mibachutz
sharei, either fire on the outside like we've been talking about,
או צריך לערות מעת לעת, o tzarich learos me'es le'es, therefore you
have to either do the water 72 hours, changing it every 24,
או לשומם עד שנים עשר חודש. o leshomam ad shenem asar chodesh.
And then he answers another interesting thing, wait 12 months. So that's
another interesting approach. You know people you know get this pottery, China
from their grandmother, is there a heter of waiting 12 months? Again,
this is a case where it absorbed with cold, but we have
not seen the waiting 12 months in the Gemara, at least not
yet. So anyway let's keep let's go back to the Gemara. But
nice to see how Rashi is applying it practically. Let's go back
to the Gemara.
Okay, איבעיא להו. iba'ya lehu. מהו לתת לתוכן שיכר? mahu lates lesochan
shechar? Okay, you can't use this
wine stuff and but... but we thought that you could put like
brine in it, what about putting like mead, like beer in it?
Maybe that'll also negate the taste or maybe that might be muttar
as well. So let's see what it says. רב נחמן ורב יהודה
אסרי. Rav Nachman u'Rav Yehuda asrei. Rav Nachman and Rav Yehuda says
it's forbidden. ורבא שרי. ve-Rava sharei. And Rava said it's permissible. Okay,
and again Rashi says a similar type of a reason that you
know the... you know that the beer counteracts the taste of the
wine. Again, not so clear: is it then permissible from that point?
Not totally clear. Anyway, Ravina רבינא Ravina sharlei שרא ליה sharlei leRav
Chiya brei deRav Yitzchak לרב חייא בריה דרב יצחק leRav Chiya brei
deRav Yitzchak lemirma bah shikra למימר בה שכרא lemirma bah shikra to
use these flasks or
these jugs for beer. Azal ramu behu chamra אזל רמו בהו
חמרא Azal ramu behu chamra so he said okay beer wine it's
all the same thing if it's muttar מותר muttar it's muttar מותר
muttar he put wine in it. Va'afillu hachi velo chash lamiltei ואפילו
הכי ולא חש למילתא Va'afillu hachi velo chash lamiltei so you might
think that the normal Rabbi would say oh clearly if I tell
people it's okay for beer they wind up using it for wine
I gotta tell them it's assur אסור assur for beer as well.
And he said no you need to teach the right halacha הלכה
halacha and if he made a mistake okay so he said you
know he said lo chash lamiltei amikrei bahlmu ולא חש למילתא אמיקרי
בעלמא lo chash lamiltei amikrei bahlmu it was totally chance that he
got it confused it is not something to change our basic teaching
that it is permissible. Rav Yitzchak bar Bisna רב יצחק בר ביסנא
Rav Yitzchak bar Bisna now Rav Yitzchak bar Bisna רב יצחק בר
ביסנא Rav Yitzchak bar Bisna havlei hanu mani de-Pakusna הוו ליה הני
מאני דפקוסטא havlei hanu mani de-Pakusna he had certain you know vessels
of Pakusna פקוסטא Pakusna which are like made out of dried dung
and also absorbed wine and melinu
maya ומלינהו מיא melinu maya and he filled it up with water
to do this kashering כשר kashering of water v'achinu beshimsha ואחינהו בשמשא
v'achinu beshimsha but he put it out in the sun paku פקעו
paku and that caused the vessels to burst. So amar lei Rav
Abba אמר ליה רב אבא amar lei Rav Abba so Rav Abba
רב אבא Rav Abba said assar tinu alaich issura de'olam אסרתינהו עלך
איסורא דלעולם assar tinu alaich issura de'olam so you now have made
it permanently forbidden meaning you destroyed your vessels by
trying to be like extra frum פרום. frum. Eima de'amar rabanan אימא
דאמרי רבנן eima de'amar rabanan when did the Rabbis רבנן rabanan say
you kasher כשר kasher it melinu maya מלינהו מיא melinu maya
just filling it with water achinu beshimsha mi amrei ואחינהו בשמשא מי
אמרי achinu beshimsha mi amrei they never told you to leave it
in the sun that was just stupid. Okay, amar Rav Hisda amar
Rav Ammi אמר רב חסדא אמר רב אמי amar Rav Hisda amar
Rav Ammi klei netara כלי נטרא klei netara
vessels of nitron which is we'll see in a minute what that
is ein lo tohara olamit אין לו טהרה עולמית ein lo tohara
olamit it can never be fully you know made kosher because it
presumably absorbs and it can't come out. Mai klei netara מאי כלי
נטרא mai klei netara what are these vessels of nitron? So amar
Rav Yosef bar Abin אמר רב יוסף בר אבין amar Rav Yosef
bar Abin klei machporot shel tzrif כלי מחפורת של צריף klei machporot
shel tzrif they're made from the diggings around of alum and they're
a type of let's see what exactly it is here.
Here's how the Koren explains it. Nitron is a mixture of sodium
carbonate that occurs naturally in colorless deposits in desert plains although in
ancient times it was often produced from seaweed. Okay, the Gemara גמרא
Gemara here indicates that people would craft vessels from earth mixed with
nitron that they would excavate together with alum
and here they add that since it often dissolves in water there's
no way to purify vessels constructed from them I'm not sure what
that means would the thing actually destroy get destroyed if you put
it in water I don't think so you were using it as
a vessel. The Gemara גמרא Gemara isn't clear why you can't kasher
כשר kasher it I mean I would have assumed more along the
lines of what we've been saying until now which is that it
absorbs without it being able to come out. But anyway mai klei
so we said that okay dvei parzik rufila דבי פרזיק רופילא dvei
parzik rufila the people of this house of Parzik who was like
an officer of the king anas hani kubi mipumbedita אנס הני כובי
מפומבדיתא anas hani kubi mipumbedita he seized forcibly seized these vessels in
Pumbedita פומבדיתא Pumbedita like the story before ramu behu chamra רמו בהו
חמרא ramu behu chamra and he put wine in them adrinu nahlai
אהדרינהו ניהליה adrinu nahlai and then he returned it so again you
have vessels that already had absorbed kosher wine but that were temporarily
used so you know again you could have sort of said wow
maybe they don't absorb anything but we've seen that that hasn't been
what we've been saying so but let's see what we say now.
Adrinu nahlai אהדרינהו ניהליה adrinu nahlai asshalu leRav Yehuda אתו שיילוה לרב
יהודה asshalu leRav Yehuda they asked Rav Yehuda רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
amar he said keivan delo machnisan lekiyomam כיון דלא מכניסן לקיומם keivan
delo machnisan lekiyomam look they didn't keep the wine in it a
long time they only used it temporarily to drink from and you
know they didn't use it for storage meshachshachan bemaya ve'in mutarin משכשכן
במיא ואינון מותרין meshachshachan bemaya ve'in mutarin just rinse it out with
water as long as there's no drips left on the inside so
that's actually interesting because it contrasts to an almost identical case we
had on the amud aleph עמוד א' amud aleph where it said
you had to kasher כשר kasher it. Maybe the case before was
one where it
was machnisan lekiyomam מכניסן לקיומם machnisan lekiyomam it was long-term and this
was temporary the Gemara גמרא Gemara does not put those two cases
in explicit you know conversation. Okay so that's that but that makes
sense if it's you know we've had cases where it's considered that
it doesn't can't really absorb like if it's brand new or whatever
so here it has all filled with kosher wine it's been used
and it's now absorbed that makes sense to say it doesn't as
long as it's not wasn't used by the non-Jews for long-term it's
not going to absorb anymore. Amar Rav Avira אמר רב אבירא amar
Rav Avira said Rav Avira רב אבירא Rav Avira hani chatzvei shachimei
הני
חצבי שחימי hani chatzvei shachimei these brown earthenware vessels d'armiya de'armaya דארמאי
דארמיה d'armiya de'armaya keivan delo bali tuva כיון דלא בלעי טובא keivan
delo bali tuva since they are not so porous meshachshachan bemaya ve'in
mutarin משכשכן במיא ואינון מותרין meshachshachan bemaya ve'in mutarin so even though
they're earthenware you know it's not like a formal definition that anything
that's earthenware you know is always going to be forbidden it's about
the metzius מציאות metzius and he says these types of things are
really not porous and it's not a problem you know when it
comes to kashering כשר kashering of vessels you know nowadays and all
these But since they are not so porous, משכשכן במים והן מותרין.
meshachshechan bemayim vehen mutarin. So even though they're earthenware, it's not like
a formal definition that anything that's earthenware is always going to be
forbidden. It's about the מציאות. metzius. And he says these types of
things are really not porous, and it's not a problem. When it
comes to kashering of vessels, nowadays in all these modern different types
of materials that they're made from, some פוסקים poskim just take a
formalist approach. Oh, well that's sort of like pottery, that's sort of
like an earthenware type of a thing, or sort of like glass,
or glass is like pottery and therefore it's totally forbidden. And others
take a much more practical approach. Let's see, does it absorb, does
it not absorb? Okay. Now again, this is all cold, but still,
it's a practical approach. אמר רב פפי, Amar Rav Pappi, said רב
פפי, Rav Pappi, הני פסווסא דבי מכסי, hani pasvasa devei Michsi, these
פסווסא pasvasa which רש״י Rashi says are certain type of earthenware vessels,
or clay vessels, of בי מכסי, bei Michsi, כיון דלא בלעו טובא,
keivan d'lo bal'u tuva, maybe that was a place, or רש״י Rashi
says it was a place that had very hard earth that it
was made from, כיון דלא בלעו טובא, keivan d'lo bal'u tuva, it's
not very absorbent, אובד קא, oved ka, so therefore משכשכן במים מותרין,
meshachshechan bemayim mutarin, then we just assume it doesn't absorb. So again,
here you have all of these cases. Is it being used long
term, short term, is it new, is it old? What type of
exact earthenware vessel it is? So that's a very מציאות metzius oriented
approach. Again, the one thing that makes this more lenient is that
we're talking about absorbing in cold. Okay.
כסי. Kassi. Now what about כסי? kassi? So רש״י Rashi says that
means like earthenware again, like a pottery
glasses, not glasses, whatever, but goblets, cups. רב אסי ואסר, Rav Assi
v'assar, רב אסי Rav Assi said it's forbidden. רב אשי שרא, Rav
Ashi shara, רב אשי Rav Ashi said it's permitted. אי שתו בהו
עובדי כוכבים פעם ראשונה כולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסור. Ei shasu behu
ovdei kochavim pa'am rishona kuli alma lo peligi d'assur. If the non-Jew
used it the first time, everybody agrees it's forbidden. It was totally
porous and it absorbed and now you have to kasher it. כי
פליגי בפעם שניה. Ki peligi befa'am sheniya. The question is if a
Jew used it first and then the non-Jew used it. Does the
fact that the Jew used it mean that it won't absorb from
the wine used by the non-Jew? איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, others say
פעם ראשונה ושניה כולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסור. pa'am rishona usheniya kuli
alma lo peligi d'assur. No, non-Jew used it either the first or
the second time, it absorbs. וכי פליגי, Veki peligi, when do we
argue? בפעם שלישית, Befa'am shelishis, on the third time. והלכתא, Vehilchasa, and
the halacha is פעם ראשונה ושניה אסור, pa'am rishona usheniya assur, בג'
מותר. be-gimel mutar. Only by the third time do we say it
absorbed of the other wine and now it won't absorb from this
wine. Now it's a little strange here because we said in the
משנה Mishna that or we said right away at the beginning of
the סוגיא sugya in the גמרא Gemara that brand new things don't
absorb, and here it is saying that the first or second time
it does absorb. So תוספות Tosafot raises a whole various questions on
רש״י Rashi along that way and he gives a whole different explanation.
רש״י Rashi presumably would have to say that the מציאות metzius is
one that the things that they made
these cups out of were particularly porous, but it's very hard to
keep
track or to try to get a consistency here because it's very
מציאות metzius oriented these discussions.
All right. אמר רב זביד Amar Rav Zevid says רב זביד, Rav
Zevid, האי מני דקוניא חיורא, hai mani dekunya chivra, so these types
of like glazed vessels, very relevant for a China discussion. These types
of glazed vessels, חיורא ואוכמא, chivra ve'uchma, if it's a white or
black earthenware, שרי, shari, it's permissible. The glaze keeps out, makes it
non-porous and therefore it doesn't absorb. Again, we're talking with cold. ירוקא
אסור, Yeroka assur, if it's green it's forbidden, משום דמצריף, mishum demitzrif,
because that has alum in it which is very absorbent. That gets
back to the earlier גמרא Gemara about this נטרון nitron which it's
very absorbent. So therefore it absorbs even though it's glazed and then
it's stuck in the vessel. ואי אית בהו קרטופני כולהו אסירא, V'ei
is behu kartufnei kulhu asira, but if it's got cracks then even
in the glaze,
then even the black ones and the white ones are forbidden.
דרש מרימר, Darash Mareimar, so מרימר Mareimar taught, קוניא, kunya, when you're
dealing with glazed vessels, בין אוכמא בין חיורא בין ירוקא, bein uchma
bein chivra bein yeroka, whether black or whether white or green, שרי,
shari, it's all permissible. More lenient approach. Okay, more lenient. But now
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, מאי שנא מחמץ בפסח? mai shana
mechametz bePesach? How is this any different than חמץ בפסח? chametz bePesach?
דבעי מיניה ממרימר, Diba'ei minei miMareimar, they asked מרימר, Mareimar, הני מני
דקוניא, hani mani dekunya, when you have these earthenware vessels which are
glazed, מהו להשתמשי בהו בפסח? mahu le'ishtamushi behu bePesach? Can you use
it by פסח? Pesach? And here by the way presumably we're talking
about that they were used with heat. So ירוקא לא תיבעי לך,
yeroka lo tibei lach, I'm not even asking about green, דמצריף ובלע,
demitzrif uvala, because it's got alum in it it absorbs and ובלע
ubala and it absorbs, ואסירא va'asira and it's forbidden. כי תיבעי לך
חיורא ואוכמא, Ki tibei lach chivra ve'uchma, I'm asking about white and
black. מאי, Mai, what's the story? כי
אית בהו קרטופני לא תיבעי לך, Ki is behu kartufnei lo tibei
lach, if it's got cracks I'm not even asking, דודאי בלעו, devadai
bal'u, that definitely absorbs, ואסירא va'asira and it's forbidden. כי תיבעי לך
דשיעא, Ki tibei lach deshia, what I'm asking, if it's smooth. מאי,
Mai, what's the הלכה? halacha? Exactly the distinctions we were making. By
the way I should also mention before you get to the answer
that רש״י Rashi says that what these are glazed with is lead,
things like lead poisoning in the ancient world. Anyway,
אמר להו, Amar lehu, so this was a question asked from מרימר
Mareimar
and he responded, אנא חזינא להו דמדייצי, Ana chazina lehu demadaytzi, I
see that they... These ones that they are, that even the smooth
ones and even the ones
that are black and white, okay, and they're smooth and they're black
and white and they have all the good qualities, I still see
that they sweat after they've been used, you know, they will produce
a sweat. וכיון דמדייצי, Vekivan demadaytzi, since they sweat, that means that,
you know, liquid is being exuded from it, ואזלי בלעי, Veazli bale'i,
then they absorb, then it's evident that even though
they're glazed, they're still going to absorb, ואסירי, Veasiri, and it's forbidden.
So here the same מריימר Maremar who said by the wine, it's
all permissible, you know, white, black, green, whatever, everything is permissible, here
when it comes to פסח, Pesach, he's more מחמיר machmir and he
says that it's all forbidden. So, you know, so what's the story?
So let's take a look. So that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara
asks. So the גמרא Gemara says, oh, we didn't finish the statement.
מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why is it forbidden? דתורה העידה על כלי
חרס שאינו יוצא מידי דופנו לעולם. Datorah eidah al kli cheres she'eino
yotzei miyedei dofno le'olam. The Torah makes it clear, you know, that
when a pottery vessel or something gets absorbed, you can't get it
out because the Torah talks about like cooking a חטאת chatas in
a pottery vessel and it says you have to destroy it. So
once it gets in, it can't come out. So if we see
that even with the glaze it's going to sweat, that shows me
that it absorbed, even though it's green and, excuse me, even though
it's black and white and even though it's glazed, and it's a
problem. So he's totally מחמיר machmir by פסח Pesach and totally מקיל
meykil by wine. What's the difference? So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי שנא מיין נסך, Mai shena miyayin nesech, how's it different than
ייין נסך yayin nesech דדרש ליה מריימר Dedarshei leih Maremar that רמימר
Remimer expounded, כולהו מאני דקוניא שרי, Kulehu manei dekunya sharei, it's all
permissible. וכי תימא חמץ דאורייתא יין נסך דרבנן, Vechi teima chametz de'oraisa
yayin nesech derabbanan, חמץ chametz is דאורייתא, de'oraisa, יין נסך yayin nesech
is דרבנן, derabbanan,
וכל דתיקון רבנן כעין דאורייתא תיקון, Vechol detikkun rabbanan ke'ein de'oraisa tikkun,
still, if it's the question of whether the vessel absorbs, we shouldn't
make a distinction whether it's, you know, דאורייתא de'oraisa or דרבנן, derabbanan,
you know, we're saying that the vessel absorbs. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אה, זה תשמישו בחמין וזהו תשמישו בצונן. Ah, zeh tashmisho bechamin
vezehu tashmisho betzonen. Finally,
we identify one of the key distinguishing points. חמץ Chametz you're using
with heat. When it gets hot, then it can absorb, really absorb
and even get through the glaze and then it stays in. If
it's cold, then the fact that it's glazed will keep it out.
So here's an example, again, that we're dealing with cold absorption, which
is a חידוש chiddush that we say it all together, and that
might lead to certain more lenient ways to כשר kasher it and
here it also means that with a glaze we don't have to
be concerned at all. Okay, we will end here.